Gaoxiong Zeng

Contact

Brief Biography

Gaoxiong Zeng (曾高雄) is a Ph.D. student in computer science at Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST), advised by Prof. Kai Chen. He received his B.E. degree in electronic engineering from University of Science and Technology of China (USTC) in 2015. His research areas of interest include computer networks and systems, with special focuses on data center networking and transport protocols.

Education

Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST)	Hong Kong, China
Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering	2015 - 2022
University of Science and Technology of China (USTC)	Hefei, China
B.E. in Electronic Engineering and Information Science	2011 - 2015

Work Experiences

[Research Intern] Peng Cheng Laboratory. Shenzhen, China.	2019.09 - 2020.01
[Research Intern] Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd. Hong Kong, China.	2018.11 - 2019.01
[Research Intern] Chinese Academy of Sciences. Beijing, China.	2014.07 - 2014.08

Publications

Conference Publications:

- Gaoxiong Zeng, Li Chen, Bairen Yi, Kai Chen. "Cutting Tail Latency in Commodity Datacenters with Cloudburst", in Proceedings of the 41th IEEE International Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM), Virtual Event, May 2-5, 2022.
- Gaoxiong Zeng, Jianxin Qiu, Yifei Yuan, Hongqiang Liu, Kai Chen. "FlashPass: Proactive Congestion Control for Shallow-buffered WAN", in Proceedings of the 29th IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP), Virtual Event, November 1-5, 2021.
- Shuihai Hu, Wei Bai, Gaoxiong Zeng, Zilong Wang, Baochen Qiao, Kai Chen, Kun Tan, Yi Wang. "Aeolus:
 A Building Block for Proactive Transport in Datacenters", in Proceedings of the Annual Conference of the
 ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication (SIGCOMM), Virtual Event, August 10-14, 2020.
- Gaoxiong Zeng, Wei Bai, Ge Chen, Kai Chen, Dongsu Han, Yibo Zhu, Lei Cui. "Congestion Control for Cross-Datacenter Networks", in Proceedings of the 27th IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP), Chicago, USA, October 7-10, 2019.
- Jiacheng Xia, Gaoxiong Zeng, Junxue Zhang, Weiyan Wang, Wei Bai, Junchen Jiang, Kai Chen. "Rethinking Transport Layer Design for Distributed Machine Learning", in Proceedings of the 3rd ACM Asia-Pacific Workshop on Networking (APNet), Beijing, China, August 17-18, 2019.
- Gaoxiong Zeng, Wei Bai, Ge Chen, Kai Chen, Dongsu Han, Yibo Zhu. "Combining ECN and RTT for Datacenter Transport", in Proceedings of the 1st ACM Asia-Pacific Workshop on Networking (APNet), Hong Kong SAR, China, August 3-4, 2017.

Journal Publications:

o Shuihai Hu, Gaoxiong Zeng, Wei Bai, Zilong Wang, Baochen Qiao, Kai Chen, Kun Tan, Yi Wang. "Aeolus: A

- Building Block for Proactive Transport in Datacenter Networks", in IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (ToN), 2021.
- Gaoxiong Zeng, Shuihai Hu, Junxue Zhang, Kai Chen. "Transport Protocols for Data Center Networks: A Survey", in ICT-CAS/CCF Journal of Computer Research and Development (J-CRAD), 57(1), 2020.
- Wei Bai, Shuihai Hu, **Gaoxiong Zeng**, Kai Chen. "Data Center Flow Scheduling", in Communications of the China Computer Federation (**CCCF**), 15(4), 2019.

Miscellaneous:

- Gaoxiong Zeng, Li Chen, Bairen Yi, Kai Chen. "Optimizing Tail Latency in Commodity Datacenters using Forward Error Correction", in arXiv:2110.15157 [cs.NI], October 28, 2021.
- Ge Chen, Gaoxiong Zeng, Li Chen. "P4COM: In-Network Computation with Programmable Switches", in arXiv:2107.13694 [cs.NI], July 29, 2021.
- Hao Wang, Jingrong Chen, Xinchen Wan, Han Tian, Jiacheng Xia, Gaoxiong Zeng, Weiyan Wang, Kai Chen,
 Wei Bai, Junchen Jiang. "Domain-specific Communication Optimization for Distributed DNN Training", in
 arXiv:2008.08445 [cs.DC], August 16, 2020.
- Shuihai Hu, Kai Chen, Gaoxiong Zeng. "Improved Path Compression for Explicit Path Control in Production Data Centers", in Poster Session of the 13th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI), Santa Clara, USA, March 16-18, 2016.

Selected Talks

[ICNP] FlashPass: Proactive Congestion Control for Shallow-buffered WAN. Virtual Event.	Nov. 2021
[ICNP] Congestion Control for Cross-Datacenter Networks. Chicago, USA.	Oct. 2019
[APNet] Combining ECN and RTT for Datacenter Transport. Hong Kong, China.	Aug. 2017

Professional Activities

[Reviewer] IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (ToN), IEEE INFOCOM, etc.

[Review Drafter] SIGCOMM 2021, NSDI 2021, INFOCOM 2021, CoNEXT 2020, SIGCOMM 2019, etc.

Teaching & Tutoring

[Teaching Assistant] HKUST FYP: Transport Design for Data Center Netw	vorks.	$Fall\ 2019,$	Spring 2020
[Teaching Assistant] HKUST COMP2611: Computer Organization.	Spring 2016,	Fall 2016,	Spring 2017

Honors & Awards

[HKUST] Research Postgraduate Scholarship.	2015, 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, 20	021
[USTC] Graduate of the Talent Program in Computer and Informati	on Science and Technology. 20	015
[USTC] Outstanding Student Scholarship (top 15% or top 30%).	2012, 2013, 20	014
[Department of Education, Guangdong] Provincial Soong Ching Ling	Scholarship. 20	010

Last updated in Dec. 2021.